<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "document-v12.dtd">
<document>

<header>
  <title>XMLBeans News</title>
</header>

<body>

<section>
<title>News and events</title>

<section>
<title>ApacheCon 2004 (13-17 November 2004)</title>

<p><link href="http://apachecon.com/2004/US/index.html">
<img src="http://apache.org/images/ac2004_170x100.gif" alt="ApacheCon 2004 Logo"/>
</link>

<link href="http://apachecon.com/2004/US/index.html">ApacheCon US 2004 </link> (13-17 November
2004).  ApacheCon is the conference for all things Apache. Come along and learn about a range of new
technologies, meet some Apache folks and share the knowledge.  See more information about Apache
Conferences.  Cliff Schmidt and Kevin Krouse are scheduled to speak about XMLBeans.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>XMLBeans 1.0.3 Released (28 June 2004)</title>

<p><link href="http://xmlbeans.apache.org/">Apache XMLBeans Team</link> has released XMLBeans Version
1.0.3.  Download version 1.0.3 from the <link
href="http://xmlbeans.apache.org/sourceAndBinaries/index.html">Source and Binaries section</link>.
</p>

<p>Version 1.0.3 is <link href="http://xmlbeans.apache.org/">Apache XMLBeans</link> first release after
becomming a Top Level Project in the <link href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software
Foundation</link>.</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>XMLBeans becomes a Top Level Apache project (25 June 2004)</title>

<p>Apache XMLBeans Project has graduated out the <link href="http://incubator.apache.org/">Apache
Incubator Project</link> to become Top Level Project in the <link
href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</link>.  Apache XMLBeans provides a
simplified model for interacting with XML documents. The project originated with a contribution from
<link href="http://www.bea.com">BEA Inc.</link>, however, after its time within the Apache
Incubator, it is now a full-fledged Apache community and codebase under Apache License 2.0. Cliff
Schmidt is the Chair of the new Apache XMLBeans PMC (Project Management Committee).  </p>

</section>

<section>
<title>XMLBeans (incubated) 1.0.2 Released (23 April 2004)</title>

<p><link href="http://xmlbeans.apache.org/">Apache XMLBeans Team</link> has released XMLBeans Version
1.0.2.  Download version 1.0.2 from the
<link href="http://xmlbeans.apache.org/sourceAndBinaries/index.html">Source and Binaries
section</link>.</p>

<p><link href="http://xmlbeans.apache.org/">Apache XMLBeans</link> is an effort undergoing <link
href="http://incubator.apache.org/">incubation</link> at the <link href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache
Software Foundation (ASF)</link>, sponsored by the <link href="http://xml.apache.org/">XML project</link>.</p>

<p>Incubation is required of all newly accepted projects until a further review indicates that the
infrastructure, communications, and decision making process have stabilized in a manner consistent
with other successful ASF projects. While incubation status is not necessarily a reflection of the
completeness or stability of the code, it does indicate that the project has yet to be fully
endorsed by <link href="http://www.apache.org/">the ASF</link>.</p>

</section>

</section>

</body>
</document>
