<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://apache.org/forrest/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
	<header>
		<title>XMLBeans Source and Binaries</title>
	</header>
	<body>
    <section>
      <title>Binary or source?</title>
      <p>
        Most users will want to download a stable release of XMLBeans.  If
        you're interested in contributing or like to live on the bleeding
        edge, you may want to compile the source for yourself.
      </p>
      <p>
        JDK 1.4 is required for XMLBeans.  If you need a version of XMLBeans
        for JDK 1.3, see the instructions on how to check out XMLBeans from
        CVS <link href="#Source+via+CVS+checkout">below</link>.  If you're
        building XMLBeans from source, you will need to have <link
          href="http://ant.apache.org/">Ant</link> installed.
      </p>
      <p>
        Once you've downloaded the distribution or checked out the source,
        you should:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>first read the README.txt</li>
        <li>read the <link href="../documentation/conInstallGuide.html">installation guide</link></li>
        <li>check out the <link href="../samples/index.html">samples</link> page</li>
        <li>check out the <link href="../documentation/index.html">documentation</link> page</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
		<section>
			<title>XMLBeans Binary and Development Kit</title>
			<p>Download XMLBeans Version 1.0.3 from one of the <link href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/xml/xmlbeans">Apache mirrors.</link>
			  You can also download from main <link href="http://www.apache.org/dist/xml/xmlbeans/">Apache Distribution Site</link></p>
			<p>You should verify the integrity of the files that you download. <link href="http://xml.apache.org/mirrors.cgi#verify">Here</link> are some
			instructions for verifying the integrity of a downloaded file</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>XMLBeans Source</title>
      <p>There are a few ways to get the XMLBeans source code.  You can
        download the source for a particular release, browse the source using
        ViewCVS, or check the source out from CVS.
      </p>
			<section>
				<title>Source via CVSView</title>
        <p>You can browse the XMLBeans source via <link href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/xml-xmlbeans/">ViewCVS</link>
				</p>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Source via CVS checkout</title>
        <p>In CVS, you will find two versions of XMLBeans and samples.  The currently
          stable version we call 'v1' and corresponds to the 1.0.3 release.
          Only bug fixes are applied to v1.  Active development is going on in
          the 'v2' version of XMLBeans.  The samples usually apply to both
          versions.</p>
				<p>If you have CVS installed on your machine you can issue the following commands to get XMLBeans source:</p>
				<source>
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic login
password: anoncvs

# get everything!
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout xml-xmlbeans

# or, just get the stable v1 version of XMLBeans
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout xml-xmlbeans/v1

# or, just get the v2 version of XMLBeans under development
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout xml-xmlbeans/v2

# or, just get the samples for XMLBeans
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout xml-xmlbeans/samples</source>
        <p>A jdk1.3 version of XMLBeans v1 was ported by Matt Bishop and is
          available only from CVS in the branch named 'xmlbeans-jdk13_branch'.
          To check that branch out from cvs, run the command:</p>
        <source>
# or, get the stable v1 version of XMLBeans for jdk13
cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic checkout -r xmlbeans-jdk13_branch xml-xmlbeans/v1</source>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Building XMLBeans</title>
        <p>XMLBeans requires that you have the Ant installed.</p>
				<section>
					<title>Windows</title>
					<p>After the steps above you should see an xml-xmlbeans directory:</p>
					<source>
cd xml-xmlbeans\v1
xbeanenv
ant</source>
					<p>This will create a build directory containing the executables.  The <code>xbean.jar</code> is in the <code>xml-beans\v1\ar</code> directory.  Try
					<code>ant -projecthelp</code> to see other build options.</p>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Unix</title>
          <p>Building on Unix or Cygwin is essentially the same as for
            Windows:</p>
					<source>
cd xml-xmlbeans/v1
xbeanenv.sh
ant</source>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
